William H. P. Blandy Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William H. P. Blandy Papers 1913-1977
MSS81522
Blandy, William H. P. (William Henry Purnell), 1890-1954
400 items
2 containers plus 4 oversize
3.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer. Correspondence, reports, speeches, biographical material, scrapbooks, and clippings relating chiefly to Blandy's World War II service as head of the United States Navy Department Bureau of Ordnance and afterward as director of Operation Crossroads, the atomic tests at Bikini Atoll in 1946.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Blandy, William H. P. (William Henry Purnell), 1890-1954.
Organizations
United States. Navy Department. Bureau of Ordnance.; United States. Navy--Officers.
Subjects
Operation Crossroads, Marshall Islands, 1946.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of William H. P. Blandy, naval officer, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1992. The deposit was converted to a gift in 1998.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Phonograph records have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the William H. P. Blandy Papers in the Naval Historical Foundation Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William H. P. Blandy are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Henry Purnell Blandy (1890-1954) span the years 1913-1977 and consist of correspondence, clippings, speeches, reports, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous biographical material. The focus is on the World War II years when Blandy headed the Naval Bureau of Ordnance and on his direction in 1946 of Operation Crossroads, the atomic tests at Bikini Atoll in the Marshall Islands.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material, subject, or personal name.
Container List
- Biographical and genealogical material, awards, and citations, 1934-1954, undated (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
- Commissions, 1939-1942 See Oversize (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Official, 1939-1950 (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1917-1977 (Box 1)
- King, Ernest J., "Our Navy at War" and United States at War, Army and Navy Journal, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
- Noyes, Leigh, 1950 (Box 1)
- Operation Crossroads (Box 1)
  - Ships (Box 1)
    - Avery Island (miscellaneous auxiliary ship), 1946 (Box 1)
    - Panamint (combined operations headquarters ship), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Shurcliff, W. A., Bombs at Bikini, 1947 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks (Box 2)
  - Florida (battleship) and other sea duty, 1918-1923 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944-1949 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - "Operation Crossroads," 1946 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - "Pictorial Record, Cruise of the Commander in Chief, Atlantic and U. S. Atlantic Fleet," 1948 See Oversize (Box 2)
- Speeches, statements, and writings (Box 2)
  - Malaval, Pierre, "Study of Transverse Resistance of Cylindrical Tubes," translated by Blandy, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Midshipman second class cruise notebook, circa 1913 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1945 (Box 2)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Commissions, 1939-1947 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
  - Scrapbooks (Box OV 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1944-1949 (Container 2) (Box OV 2)
    - "Operation Crossroads," 1946 (Container 2) (Box OV 3)
    - "Pictorial Record, Cruise of the Commander in Chief, Atlantic and U. S. Atlantic Fleet," 1948 (Container 2) (Box OV 4)